Light roast, dark roast, low-acid?
Are there different health benefits
to these different kinds of coffee?
Watch the video to find out.
"Which Coffee Is Healthier -
Light Roast, Dark Roast, or Low Acid?"
For those drinking non-paper-
filtered coffee, like boiled,
French press, or Turkish coffee,
the amount of cholesterol-
raising compounds
in the lightest roast coffee
may be twice as high
compared to using
very dark roast beans.
So, it appears some of the cholesterol-
raising compounds are destroyed by roasting;
so, in this case darker
would be better, or…
you can just use a paper filter
and eliminate 95 percent
of the cholesterol-raising
activity of coffee regardless
of the roast as I’ve described before.
But I did another video showing
dark roasting may also destroy
up to nearly 90 percent of
the chlorogenic acids,
which are the antioxidant,
anti-inflammatory phytonutrients
purported to account for
many of coffee’s benefits.
So, in that case, light
roast would be better.
On the other hand, dark roasting
can wipeout up to 99.8 percent
of pesticides in conventionally
grown coffee,
and more than 90 percent
of a fungal contaminant
called ochratoxin, which is
a potent kidney toxin found
in a wide range of food ingredients
that can get moldy.
But then, what about the polycyclic
aromatic hydrocarbon products
of combustion that are suspected
to be carcinogenic and DNA damaging?
Darker roasts may have up to four
times more than light roasts.
Thus, they advocate controlling
roasting conditions
to cut down on these
combustion compounds.
Just to put things in perspective,
even the darkest roast coffee
might only max out at a fraction of
a nanogram of benzopyrene per cup—
considered to be the most
toxic of these compounds—
whereas a single medium
portion of grilled chicken
could have over 1,000 times more.
Overall, you don’t know
if light versus dark roast
is better until you…
put it to the test.
This study found that dark roast coffee
is more effective than light roast coffee
in reducing body weight.
Folks were randomized to a month
of drinking two cups a day
of light roast coffee
or dark roast coffee,
roasted from the same
batch of green coffee beans.
And in normal weight subjects
it didn’t seem to matter—
no significant weight
changes either month—
but in overweight study subjects,
they ended up about six pounds lighter
drinking dark roast coffee
compared to light roast coffee;
more than a pound a week lost just
drinking a different type of coffee.
What about light versus dark
in relation to blood sugars?
We've known since 2015 that
even a single cup of coffee
can affect the blood sugar response.
Here’s the blood sugar spike over two
hours after drinking a cup of coffee
with more than a dozen sugar cubes in it
(like a quarter cup of
sugar in one cup of coffee)
compared to the spike from the same
amount of sugar in just plain water.
What is not known is whether
this increase in blood sugars
is actually clinically meaningful.
After all, coffee consumption does not
seem to increase the risk of diabetes,
and if you compare light roast
coffee to dark roast coffee
right before chugging down
about 20 teaspoons of sugar,
there didn’t appear to be any difference.
Perhaps the take home
message is: light or dark,
maybe we shouldn’t be adding
20 spoonfuls of sugar.
And finally, what about
the effect of different roasts
on heartburn and stomach upset?
We’ll find out next.
“Dark roast coffee is more
effective than light roast coffee
in reducing body weight,”
but what about the effect
of different roasts
on heartburn and stomach upset?
We know that “coffee consumption
is sometimes associated
with symptoms of stomach discomfort;”
and so, researchers stuck pH
probes down into people’s stomachs
to measure the amount of stomach acid
generated by different types of coffee.
The way you chart stomach
acid secretion in the stomach
is called a “gastrogram.”
You basically give people
some baking soda,
which starts out alkaline, and
measure the pH in the stomach
to see how long it takes the
body to restore the stomach
back down into an acid bath:
about 15, 20 minutes.
But if you mix that same amount of
baking soda with dark roast coffee,
it takes longer, meaning
the dark roast coffee
is suppressing stomach acid secretion,
since it takes longer
to normalize the pH.
Give people more of a medium
roast coffee, though,
and we see a dramatically
different effect—
an acceleration of stomach
acid secretion,
returning the stomach to acidic
conditions three times faster
than drinking dark roast
coffee, hence the title:
“..[dark roast coffee] is less effective
at stimulating [stomach] acid secretion…
compared to a medium roast [coffee]”,
but you don’t know if that translates
into symptoms—clinical effects—
until you put it to the test.
“The most commonly used
coffee bean roasting process
is referred to as convection or ‘flash’
roasting,” which just takes a few minutes.
“An alternative method
is conduction roasting,”
which roasts at a lower temperature
for a longer time—hours—
and this results in
so-called low acid coffee.
And, supposedly, there are anecdotes
from coffee-sensitive individuals
suggesting that this low-acid coffee
“does not precipitate
or aggravate heartburn.”
When you look up that citation,
though, they just cite data
from the Puroast Coffee company,
makers of low acid coffee.
It should therefore come to no surprise
that it was the same company
that funded the study.
If you go their website, they claim that
“the health benefits associated with drinking
Puroast Low Acid coffee will
become almost immediately obvious
to those who suffer from acid
reflux, heartburn, or indigestion”,
with over 90 percent of customers
surveyed receiving symptom relief;
and so, they decided to put
their money where mouth was.
But before I get to the results,
it’s important to realize that
when they say low acid, they’re
not talking about stomach acid;
they’re talking about roasting
so long that they destroy
more of the chlorogenic
acid within the coffee bean.
You know the antioxidant, polyphenol,
phytonutrient chlorogenic acid...
You know the anti-diabetic, anti-cancer,
anti-inflammatory,
anti-obesity antioxidant...
but that’s like some orange juice
company going out of their way
to destroy the vitamin C and then
branding their OJ as “low acid.”
And, that would be technically
true—vitamin C is ascorbic acid—
but they’d be bragging about
destroying some of the nutrition,
and that’s exactly what low
acid coffee makers are doing.
But hey, if it causes less stomach
discomfort maybe it’s worth it?
Thirty coffee-sensitive
individuals completed
a randomized, double-blind, crossover
study in which the symptoms
of heartburn, regurgitation,
and stomach upset were assessed
following the consumption of the
Puroast brand low acid coffee
versus conventionally roasted
regular Starbucks coffee,
and to the funder’s chagrin,
no benefit whatsoever was found
with the low acid coffee.
Consumption of both coffees
resulted in heartburn, regurgitation,
and stomach upset in most individuals.
So much for that ridiculous
90 percent-of-customers claim.
No significant differences
in the frequency or severity
of heartburn, regurgitation, or
dyspepsia were demonstrated
between the two coffees, either in a
fasting state or after a test meal.
They couldn’t find any way to make
the low acid coffee look better.
So, they had this initial thought
that a difference in coffee acidity
may explain the company’s claims;
however, when put to the test
in a randomized, controlled study,
they found no difference in symptoms,
suggesting the whole coffee
acidity thing doesn’t explain
the sensitivity some people
have, and I think further,
acts as a reminder that we
should never believe claims
made by anyone trying
to sell us something.